<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Inquiries into the general catalogue of diseases shewing the errrors and contradictions of that establishment with a new scheme representing more truly, and essentially, the various diseased state of humane nature / by E.M. Med D.</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5399</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12025039</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12025039</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52628</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 571:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Inquiries into the general catalogue of diseases shewing the errrors and contradictions of that establishment with a new scheme representing more truly, and essentially, the various diseased state of humane nature / by E.M. Med D.</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 7.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end [p. 7]: London, Old Southampton Buildings, over against Grays-Inn, 1691.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Nosology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="medical_text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52628:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>INQUIRIES Into the General Catalogue of Diſeaſes</head>
            <head type="sub">SHEWING The <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Contradictions</hi> of that <hi>Eſtabliſhment.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">With a new <hi>Scheme</hi> Repreſenting more Truly, and <hi>Eſſentially;</hi> the various <hi>Diſeaſed</hi> State of <hi>Humane</hi> Nature.</head>
            <byline>By E. M. Med. D.</byline>
            <p>IN the laſt Sheet <hi>(Practice of Phyſick duly Regulated)</hi> having there ſhewed, the <hi>Safety</hi> and Great Prudence of the Profeſſors, in the management of the <hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> Practice; being guarded by the Phyſicians perſonal labour in, and cuſtody of <hi>Medicines:</hi> Thereby, not only ſecuring the Art: from <hi>Invaſion</hi> by Aliens; and <hi>Patients,</hi> from <hi>Caſualties;</hi> but alſo Enriching the <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> with ſuch a ſtock of moſt requiſite Knowledge in Pharmaceutic Preparations; as enables them to deſign and provide the moſt hopeful curing Medicines, that <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> can acquire.</p>
            <p>Alſo I there ſet forth the <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>hazards:</hi> attending the genteel new Mode of preſcribing to the Shops; (a late Invention) this Practice appearing <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent</hi> in many reſpects, as proved by nine diſtinct <hi>Arguments;</hi> differently pointing at ſeveral great failings; and convicting the folly of that unreaſonable Innovation; which draws a long Tail of unavoidable Injuries, the chiefeſt <hi>remora</hi> to the Progreſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this Art.</p>
            <p>Having thus determined upon the two Modes of Practice, <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Modern;</hi> and alſo upon our tripple diviſion of Medicines relating thereto; reſpecting <hi>Latitude</hi> and <hi>Adaptation:</hi> I proceed forwards to the matter of Practice; and as the <hi>baſis</hi> thereof, I ſhall firſt Examine the Catalogue of Diſeaſes, appearing to me over-grown, and out of due form.</p>
            <p>'Tis worth remarking, from whence, or how this <hi>Regiſter</hi> of Diſeaſes did increaſe ſo greatly; when as their number (much better and truer) might have been caſt up with fewer figures; and the Practice of Phyſick, more eaſie and intelligible; for, the number of Diſeaſes, unneceſſarily multiplied, and <hi>falſly</hi> denominated, muſt needs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce diverſity of ill <hi>Methods,</hi> and great variety of injurious <hi>Medicines;</hi> which renders this Art ſo perplext and difficult, as ſcarcely to be comprehended by Humane Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and the attempts of Healing ſo often fruſtraneous: For this great <hi>Liſt</hi> of Diſeaſes being <hi>hundreds,</hi> muſt require a vaſt number of <hi>Medicines; thouſands</hi> to anſwer the Practice thereof, as you manage the Matter: For <hi>Indications</hi> being various and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in every Sick Man's Caſe; therefore all of them (you ſay) requiring different Medicines <hi>adapt</hi> to thoſe caſes by <hi>Appropriate</hi> new mixtures: thus the number of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52628:2"/>are become numberleſs, and the Practice of Phyſick incomprehenſible; and no man is able to be Maſter of this <hi>Art</hi> (in your way) if he were to live a 1000 years, but muſt alwaies be deviſing, gheſſing <hi>ex tempore,</hi> and venturing at uncertain unproved Medicines: thus practiſing <hi>fortuitouſly,</hi> with doubt and hazard all the days of his life.</p>
            <p>The Number of <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> muſt needs be unneceſſarily and falſly multiplied; when <hi>Symptoms, Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Products,</hi> bear the names of Diſeaſes, which ought otherwiſe to be diſtinguiſhed by their proper names; then failure in curing may reaſonably be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, when the <hi>Phyſician</hi> aims at the wrong mark, not rightly diſcerning one from the other: But if Diſeaſes were reduced to their true number in <hi>Scheme;</hi> they would ſooner be found out in <hi>Practice,</hi> and their Cures more ſafely and frequently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: But as they ſtand <hi>regimented</hi> with other preternatural effects (erroneouſly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be Diſeaſes, and proſecuted as ſuch) Hereby Diſeaſes truly denominated are much obſcured, often overſeen, and ſomething elſe aimed at; tyring the <hi>Patient</hi> with improper and fruſtraneous means. To illuſtrate and prove theſe Aſſertions, I ſhall give you ſome eminent <hi>Examples,</hi> in their due place.</p>
            <p>After various Opinions, controverted by the Learned of this Faculty, in determining upon Diſeaſes; as to the <hi>Notion, Denomination, Number,</hi> and <hi>Diviſion</hi> of them: I find the reſult thereof, by the Majority and better Judgments of the <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> to reſt in this Eſtabliſhment following; received and approved by the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of this preſent time: The which I ſhall now lay before you; and then make my Exceptions.</p>
            <p>The General <hi>Catalogue</hi> of Diſeaſes, is ſet forth and compriſed under theſe three <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions,</hi> thus diſtinguiſhed: <hi>Similar, Organical,</hi> and <hi>Common.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Morbus Similaris eſt morbus ex inconvenienti qualitatum contemporatione reſultans.</hi> Similar Diſeaſes are ſuch as ariſe from the inconvenient contemporation or diſproportion of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; Firſt, Second, or Occult. The firſt qualities, are four: <hi>Hot, Cold, Moiſt, Dry:</hi> either of theſe in Exceſs, make a Diſeaſe <hi>Simple:</hi> and any two of theſe qualities exceeding, make a Diſeaſe <hi>Compound:</hi> ſo that there are four <hi>Similar Simple;</hi> and four <hi>Similar Compound</hi> Diſeaſes. Both theſe, <hi>Simple</hi> and <hi>Compound,</hi> admit of another diviſion: In temperature with <hi>Matter,</hi> and without <hi>Matter:</hi> and each of theſe diviſions, <hi>(cum &amp; ſine materia;)</hi> make four Diſeaſes more diſtinct from the former. There is yet another ſubdiviſion; <hi>equal</hi> and <hi>unequal. Intemperies qualibet, ſive ſimplex fuerit, ſive compoſita; materiamque conjunctam habuerit, ſive non; duplex eſt: aequalis vel inaequalis;</hi> the words of one of your beſt Authors. From theſe Qualities were Temperaments denominated, and diſtinguiſhed; as alſo Diſeaſes called Diſtempers. The ſecond qualities being Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the five External Senſes, are theſe: <hi>Odours, Colours, Sounds, Sapors, Tactils;</hi> when Preternatural, theſe alſo are <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes, and they are accounted many. <hi>Occult</hi> qualities inconveniently mixed, make <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes likewiſe; called alſo <hi>Morbi totius ſubſtantiae.</hi> Theſe qualities when preternatural to make a Diſeaſe; they will have them to be ſeated in the <hi>Similar</hi> parts of the Body, (therefore called <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes) as <hi>Bone, Ligament, Tendon, Nerve, Veine, Artery,</hi> &amp;c. contradiſtinct to Organical Diſeaſes, that affect Organical and <hi>Diſſimilar</hi> Parts: as <hi>Heart, Ventricle, Muſcle, Eyes, Ears, Noſe,</hi> &amp;c. Here are <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes ſet forth very ſpeciouſly, amply and nicely: much pains beſtowed to little purpoſe; all this will come to nothing in the ſequel of our Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Now Gentlemen of this <hi>Robe;</hi> I muſt direct ſome of my diſcourſe to you; who know this to be a ſhort and true account of the firſt diviſion of the general <hi>Triplicity:</hi> and before I go farther, I muſt remark upon what hath been ſaid, ſhewing the Incongruities, Errors, and Contradictions thereof. When I was a <hi>Preſcriber</hi> to the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52628:2"/>
               <hi>Shops,</hi> (many years ago) I was a zealous obſerver of this Doctrine, becauſe I knew no better, being led by Books: and probably I was guilty of doing hurt thereby: but I did it through ignorance (as many do now following that Road) which mitigates the guilt <hi>à tanto.</hi> But 30 years Practice ſince, in another thinking and working way, and proving of Medicines; hath informed me better things.</p>
            <p>I perceive now, and am well ſatisfied; that Writers too much follow the general <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> of Opinions; who take them up, and ſet them down again for truth, without a ſtrict and ſerious perpenſion: and I doubt <hi>Practiſers</hi> are drawn into the like ſnare, by being too <hi>credulous</hi> of Authors; when the greateſt <hi>ſafety</hi> in Practice, does depend upon the ſecurity and certainty of Medicines of their own deſign, <hi>Manufacture, Melioration,</hi> and <hi>Probation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deſign of this <hi>Art,</hi> being to find out and ſubdue Diſeaſes; if they ſtand not right in the general <hi>Catalogue,</hi> there to be found, and truly diſtinguiſhed; inquiries after them, and means intended againſt them will be diſappointed. Setting forth Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes in their due <hi>Claſſes,</hi> is the <hi>Baſis</hi> of Practice: if the firſt general diviſions be <hi>falſe;</hi> the ſubdiviſions contained under them muſt needs be wrong; and ſuch Errors runs through, and perverts the whole Practice of this Art: as will appear when we examine the Diſeaſes of the ſeveral <hi>Regions</hi> of the Body; and in them the Diſeaſes of <hi>particular</hi> Parts: Nor is it barely an Error of <hi>denomination;</hi> but a <hi>fundamental</hi> Error; making that a Diſeaſe which is not; and the whole Proſecution Erroneous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Morbus Similaris!</hi> there is no ſuch thing in Nature; nor <hi>praeter naturam:</hi> This firſt <hi>diviſion</hi> therefore of the General <hi>Catalogue,</hi> containing <hi>Similar</hi> Difeaſes, I muſt ſtrike quite out: as not being capable to ſtand amongſt the number of Diſeaſes, being not of that <hi>Tribe;</hi> but appertaining elſewhere, and otherwiſe denominated more truly: and thus one third of Diſeaſes have injuriouſly been added. But to ſentence the Judgments and Approbations of former <hi>Ages,</hi> and the concurrence of the <hi>Learned</hi> of this preſent time, without ſufficient Reaſons and good Proof, would incur a cenſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Res praeter naturam ſunt tres: Morbus, morbi cauſa, &amp; Symptoma.</hi> There are three things, preternatural, moſt conſiderable and rightly to be diſtinguiſhed; elſe great Errors in Practice will ariſe from thence, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Morbific</hi> Cauſe, the Diſeaſe, and the <hi>Symptom.</hi> The <hi>Morbific</hi> Cauſe generates a Diſeaſe; the Diſeaſe beg ets <hi>Symptoms.</hi> All <hi>Preternaturals</hi> are compriſed under theſe three Heads, or reduceable thereto: Then Qualities <hi>Preternatural,</hi> muſt fall into one of theſe <hi>Claſſes;</hi> but to which of them they belong to is the queſtion in hand.</p>
            <p>If Qualities <hi>preternatural</hi> do affurge from <hi>Morbific</hi> Cauſes and Diſeaſes, as the <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> thereof; then Qualities cannot be <hi>Diſeaſes:</hi> But <hi>Qualities</hi> preternatural are ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, <hi>ergo:</hi> the <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition needs no Proof; the <hi>Minor</hi> appears plainly thus. Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties being <hi>Accidents,</hi> have no exiſtence of themſelves ſeparately; but are dependant upon <hi>Subſtantial</hi> Cauſes, both in their <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Preternatural</hi> State: So that Qualities act not but by the vertue and power of their Subſtances on which they depend, and <hi>iſſue</hi> from; Therefore when they are unduely exalted <hi>preternaturally,</hi> they are inſtrumental, ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and attendant upon <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>Morbific</hi> Cauſes as the product thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That which is but a <hi>Symptom</hi> of a Diſeaſe, is no Diſeaſe: But Qualities preternatural are <hi>Symptoms; Ergo:</hi> the <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition I prove from the definition of a <hi>Symptom. Symptoma eſt Accidens praeternaturam Morbum ſequens, velut umbra Corpus.</hi> In this definition are qualities preternatural compriſed <hi>(Cui convenit definitio, ei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit definitum)</hi> as properly belonging to the Tribe of <hi>Symptoms;</hi> and that they are ſo, I ſhall ſingle out one of your Principal <hi>Similar Diſeaſes (Intemperies calida)</hi> a hot Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and ſhew you that this Quality in exceſs is plainly a <hi>Symptom</hi> aſſurging from, and depending upon a <hi>Subſtantial</hi> cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52628:3"/>
Natural Heat is a <hi>ſignal</hi> of humane Life; and quite <hi>cold</hi> is one ſign of a dead Body: So that Heat appears, and diſappears, as the Life is preſent, or abſent; and ſhewing the State thereof. If that be temperate, the vital <hi>Principle</hi> (which is the Life) is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid and quiet; but when intemperate Heat appears, the vital governing Principle, is diſturb'd in its oeconomy, <hi>aeſtuates</hi> and grows hot, as offended by ſome <hi>Morbous</hi> cauſe: So that Heat riſeth and falls, with the ſtate and condition of the <hi>vital</hi> Principle; and is a <hi>Symptom</hi> and effect thereof, ſignally declaring. <hi>Intemperies calida,</hi> this hot Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature, is not; cannot be called a Diſeaſe; but is the <hi>Symptom</hi> dependant upon, and the <hi>Effect</hi> of a Diſeaſe, or <hi>Morbific</hi> Cauſe, irritating the <hi>vital</hi> Principle which is the Fountain of Heat; for, ſo ſoon as the life is extinct, the Heat vaniſheth totally.</p>
            <p>'Tis daily obvious to thoſe who are converſant with the Sick, that moſt Diſeaſes have <hi>Preternatural</hi> Heat attending them; and this as a <hi>Symptom,</hi> giving notice that the Governour <hi>(Spiritus impetum faciens)</hi> and the oeconomy or government is diſordered and diſturbed by ſome <hi>Morbous</hi> cauſe, requiring the Phyſicians help: which heat, not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded otherwiſe than as <hi>ſignal;</hi> but the <hi>Morbific</hi> cauſe to be inquired after, and the Diſeaſe planted thereby; and to them Medicines muſt level at: So that <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Cold, Moiſt,</hi> and <hi>Dry,</hi> theſe Symptomatical Qualities are cured of courſe, when the Diſeaſes are cured, on which they depend: But if you begin with curing theſe qualities, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractly from their dependencies; you begin at the wrong end; and ſuch ways of curing are like to have no end; at leaſt not by ſuch your endeavours. If this be not allowed for truth; the Doctrine of <hi>Symptoms</hi> is deſtroyed; which is rational and uſeful in Practice; and the preternatural triplicity <hi>(Morbus, morbi cauſa, &amp; Symptoma)</hi> is made void and fictitious.</p>
            <p>To ſpare farther arguments in this matter; if I prove qualities preternatural to be <hi>Symptoms,</hi> by the ſame Authors that before made them <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes; then I need no farther Proof but their own contradiction: and I find it ſo in that part of <hi>Patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia</hi> called <hi>Symptomatica;</hi> where <hi>Symptoms</hi> are generally divided into theſe three parts. <hi>Actio laeſa, excretorum &amp; retentorum vitium, &amp; qualitates mutatae.</hi> In this third Branch of the Diviſion, I find <hi>Qualities</hi> preternatural, and in their due place: But why Authors that made them leading the <hi>Van</hi> amongſt <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes; ſhould now make them bring up the <hi>Reer</hi> of <hi>Symptoms;</hi> how comes this about? Qualities are not of that <hi>Protean</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to appear <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> in one place, and <hi>Symptoms</hi> in another; that cannot be; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially without reſpect to ſome particular and extraordinary caſe.</p>
            <p>I wonder this falſe Doctrine of <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes, ſhould paſs through ſo many Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies of years; and through the Hands and Heads of ſo many Learned Writers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a reform: and why the intemperature of Qualities ſhould be ſo confined to the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milar</hi> Parts only, to make Diſeaſes there (and thereby denominated) and not in <hi>Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milar</hi> Parts alſo, I know no reaſon, and they can give none: but on the contrary I know, that ſuch intemperate preternatural <hi>Qualities</hi> does ſpread and affect <hi>Diſſimilar Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganical</hi> Parts alſo; both the firſt and ſecond Qualities; which latter are peculiar to the Organs of <hi>Senſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee plainly that <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes are improperly ſo denominated, and to be expunged out of the number of Diſeaſes: and thus the firſt diviſion of the <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue</hi> is ſet aſide, as injuriouſly put forth; which miſchiefs more evidently will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Practice, when I come to treat of particular Diſeaſes, and <hi>Symptomatical</hi> affects. As for the <hi>Occult</hi> Qualities; (alſo accounted <hi>Similar</hi> Diſeaſes) if I knew where to find them; I ſhou'd put them into their right place: But ſince we know not what they are, nor where they are; let them paſs at this time, until you give me a better account of them.</p>
            <p>I muſt remark from hence; that whereas this firſt Diviſion of the <hi>Catalogue,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52628:3"/>many ſuppoſed Diſeaſes (which are but <hi>Symptoms</hi>) appearing more frequently in Practice, than all the reſt; we may reaſonanbly conclude, that erroneous and falſe proſecutions, have engroſſed the Major part of the buſineſs in this <hi>Art:</hi> And then, if contrary <hi>Methods,</hi> and improper adapted <hi>Medicines</hi> will kill; How many Thouſands do you think have been ſent into the other World, by ſuch Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? I'le leave the number to your thoughts; this Account is too great for my A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetick: But when I come to examine the falſe Doctrine of <hi>Fevers,</hi> and the Practice thereupon; you may better compute the total of the Slain.</p>
            <p>I am amazed to think, and ſorry to declare; that the Art of curing ſhould ſo frequently be the occaſion of <hi>Killing:</hi> But much of this ariſeth from want of true knowledge, in diſtinguiſhing <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> from other preternaturals: for let us look back and ſee what Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſers have been doing; I find they have been very buſie in curing of <hi>Symptoms,</hi> when they ſhould endeavour the eradicating of Diſeaſes; they catcht at the ſhadow, but could not ſee the Body: <hi>Symptoma ſequitur Morbum, ut umbra Corpus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis commonly and well ſaid; a Diſeaſe found out is half the cure: but if the <hi>noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of a Diſeaſe in general be not truly ſtated, and rightly underſtood; we cannot eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine that the knowledge of particular Diſeaſes can be attained, but by this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary introduction: For if you miſtake in the general conception and <hi>notion</hi> of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, you err <hi>fundamentally,</hi> and then cures will be performed but <hi>accidentally:</hi> and that there is a failure in the general <hi>notion;</hi> does appear from the definition of a Diſeaſe in general, by conſent of Authors thus defined. <hi>Morbus eſt affectus corporis viventis praeter na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam, a quo functio laeditur primum.</hi> The general definition ſhould give light into the knowledge of particular Diſeaſes; but this is a dark Lanthorn. I ſhould be loth to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture my life upon the mean knowledge contained in this definition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Morbus eſt affectus</hi>] that's <hi>ignotum per aeque ignotum.</hi> The firſt part of this definition, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth not a Diſeaſe from a Symptom; for, <hi>Symptoma eſt affectus corporis viventis praeter naturam:</hi> The latter part; <hi>à quo functio laeditur primum;</hi> this diſtinguiſheth not the Diſeaſe from the morbific Cauſe: for, <hi>cauſae morbificae, ſunt res omnes aptae corpora noſtra quomodo cunque alterando immutare, &amp; a ſalubri ſtatu deturbare.</hi> Here is ſomething of a diſeaſe deſcribed <hi>(a poſteriori)</hi> in it's effects; but we ſhould have it <hi>(a priori)</hi> in its cauſes. This definition ſetting forth and ſtating the <hi>notion,</hi> and <hi>ratio formalis</hi> of a Diſeaſe in general; is the Standard whereby we are to take our meaſures of all Diſeaſes in particular: and this ought to be clear from all ambiguities; to ſtand diſtinct and ſeparate from all other Preternaturals. <hi>Scire eſt per cauſas cognoſcere:</hi> This definition ought to ſhew what a Diſeaſe is, in its eſſential cauſes <hi>(non per genus &amp; differentiam)</hi> efficient and material: but upon this neglect and overſight ſuppoſed Diſeaſes have been foiſted into the general Catalogue; which ought not to ſtand there, but belongs to another <hi>Tribe</hi> of Preternaturals.</p>
            <p>The miſapprehenſion of a Diſeaſe in the <hi>notion</hi> of it; muſt needs make a falſe <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue;</hi> and a falſe <hi>Catalogue</hi> muſt neceſſarily beget <hi>male</hi> practice; your definition of a Diſeaſe not being <hi>true (Conſequenter)</hi> then your knowledge of a Diſeaſe is not true alſo: the miſchiefs from thence in the deſigns of curing may eaſily be imagined. But to pull down and not to build up, is but half the work incumbent upon me: it remains therefore I ſhould ſet forth the nature of a Diſeaſe, in terms more intelligible and uſeful in Practice.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> in the true notion of it, is beſt known by comparing it with <hi>Health;</hi> that being a deviation from this. <hi>Sanity</hi> or <hi>Health</hi> is a perfect ſtate of the inviſible life, or <hi>vital</hi> governing Principle; acting in a viſible <hi>organized</hi> Body, and duly conſtituted to perform vital Actions: <hi>Econtra;</hi> Diſeaſe <hi>(generatim)</hi> is the pravity, deviation or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52628:4"/>Defection of the <hi>vital Principle</hi> in it ſelf; or impedited by unfitneſs of the <hi>Body</hi> to act vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal functions.</p>
            <p>From hence you may take notice, that man being compoſed of two parts; the one <hi>Active,</hi> governing by <hi>vital</hi> irradiating power: The other <hi>Paſſive,</hi> governed by reception of that influx: So that hereby there are Diſeaſes ariſing from the imbecility, enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and defection of the <hi>vital Agent;</hi> as alſo from the fragility, decay and ineptitude of the Paſſive <hi>Body:</hi> And that ſome Diſeaſes do ariſe from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Life (Spiritus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petum faciens)</hi> and others by the frailty and indiſpoſition of the <hi>Body.</hi> But Phiſicians wrongfully have charged all the declenſions and <hi>Morbous</hi> alterations, upon bodily imbeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and decay (<hi>witneſs the</hi> Catalogue <hi>of Diſeaſes</hi>) they being unacquainted with, and not diſcerning the Diſeaſes of male adminiſtration; ariſing meerly from the inſtability, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation, defections and irregularities of the vital <hi>governing</hi> Power: So that in the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed <hi>Catalogue,</hi> I find many Diſeaſes <hi>more</hi> than ſhould be; and <hi>ſome</hi> left out, that ought to be in.</p>
            <p>Our learned men have taken great pains to ſearch the Frame and fabrick of man's Body; to <hi>anatomiſe</hi> and view the viſible Parts: but the <hi>governing</hi> ruling power which moves all in this <hi>Machine;</hi> that hath been ſlighted over, and overlook'd; as if not concern'd in <hi>Bodily</hi> Diſeaſes; when as this commonly bears the chiefeſt part, in all <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bous</hi> alterations. Does any part ſuffer as diſeaſed, but the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> is concern'd? ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the firſt irregular mover, or elſe is drawn into conſent, and complies to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and fixing of the Diſeaſe, by enormity thereof. <hi>Quicquid in ſanis edit actiones ſanas; id ipſum in Morbis edit actiones vitiatas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having noted the errors and defects of the old <hi>Catalogue</hi> of Diſeaſes, and caſhered the firſt general diviſion thereof; I ſhall now draw out a new <hi>Scheme;</hi> and turn that general <hi>Triplicity</hi> (of <hi>Simliar, Organical,</hi> and <hi>Common</hi>) into a duality. Compriſing all under theſe two Heads. Diſeaſes are either <hi>Spirital,</hi> or <hi>Corporal.</hi> But by this general diviſion, I do not mean ſuch a perfect ſeparation in forming Diſeaſes, as if the one did make a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſo diſtinct from the other, as not to participate, and be unconcern'd in partnerſhip: but to ſhew that one ſide is more eminently concern'd to bear the Character of <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> and to have the <hi>Denomination;</hi> and where the ſtreſs of the Cure does chiefly lye, and to be aimed at.</p>
            <p>Spirital <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> are diſtinguiſhed by their cauſes, from whence they ariſe and are procured, and ſuch Cauſes are twofold: <hi>External</hi> and <hi>Internal. Spirital</hi> Diſeaſes that are raiſed or produced <hi>(ab extra)</hi> from outward Cauſes, are commonly called Paſſions; as <hi>Anger, Grief, Fear, Melancholy, Deſpair, Love, Jealouſie, Madneſs, Extaſie, &amp;c.</hi> and theſe I conſider, not in relation to <hi>Divinity</hi> or <hi>Morality,</hi> but as aberrations and deviations from the rectitude and ſteddineſs of <hi>Government</hi> in <hi>Humane</hi> Bodies: And thus in a Natural Senſe, theſe Paſſions are evil, and are Diſeaſes of the <hi>Vital</hi> governing Spirit; and produce bad effects, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural alterations proportionate, as theſe <hi>Paſſions</hi> are in degree more or leſs turbulent, violent and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: And that theſe you call <hi>Paſſions,</hi> are Diſeaſes, as truly and properly, as Corporal Diſeaſes; I might prove from their <hi>Cauſes</hi> preternatural, by their <hi>Diagnoſtic</hi> Signs declaring them ſo; and by the <hi>Symptoms</hi> that attend and follow, as the Products thereof: but I muſt not enlarge now upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spirital</hi> Diſeaſes <hi>(ab intra)</hi> are occaſioned by <hi>morbific</hi> Cauſes, generated within the Body; and from hence the vital <hi>Spirit</hi> ſuffers, is put by and forced out of its ſedateneſs and regularity of Government; or elſe ſpontaneouſly makes a defection and deviation in Government, by Natural debility and proneneſs to ſwerve, from lapſed Nature; the Vital Principle <hi>(Spiritus impetum faciens)</hi> not being ſo ſtrong, vigorous, and ſtable, in ſome Perſons, as in others; naturally ſo from their <hi>Progenitors;</hi> or by their different <hi>(vitae genus)</hi> Education and Manner of Living.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spirital Diſeaſes</hi> thus cauſed, are ſuch as theſe: <hi>Debility, Ebriety, Aeſtuation, Laſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Perturbation, Syncope, Epilepſy, Apoplexy, Palſy, Rigor, Sopor, Algor, Agues, Procellae ſpiritus impetum facientis;</hi> Pains <hi>(à cauſa quacunque)</hi> complaints of the Vital Principle grieved; <hi>Hyſteric</hi> Fits, <hi>Hypochondriac</hi> Melancholy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52628:4"/>
But ſome may ſay; what hath a Phyſician to do with <hi>Paſſions,</hi> ſince there is no <hi>Phyſick</hi> to cure a diſeaſed mind? I anſwer; there is advice to be given for avoiding them; and the Phyſician ought to know if his Patient labours and ſuffers under, or by them; and there is <hi>Phyſick</hi> againſt the Impreſſions and Effects wrought from thence: For what cauſes ſoever, alienates the <hi>Vital</hi> Principle from rectitude in Government, and makes an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Body; a <hi>Phyſician</hi> ought to take cognizance of them, and his meaſures thereby, in the deſign of Curing, eſpecially if ſuch Cauſes continue in being. The <hi>Vital</hi> Spirit alſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and ſuffers under the like Paſſions, from Moleſting, Irritating, and Seducing <hi>morbific</hi> Cauſes, generated within the Body, as it doth by external provoking and procuring Cauſes; ſo that the <hi>Paſſions</hi> are much what the ſame, and produce the ſame ill effects, be the Cauſes outward or inward. Hence we may learn and know, what it is that acts the chiefeſt part, in theſe preternatural <hi>morbous</hi> alterations; and what is to be aimed at, for reduction to a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good State, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſanitas conſiſt it in vita integra, ita Morbus, in ipſamet vita oblaeſa.</hi> Helmont.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corporal</hi> Diſeaſes are ſuch as reſult from preternatural undue Conformation and Conſtitution of the viſible Corporeal Parts. Such Diſeaſes are either in <hi>Magnitude,</hi> in <hi>Figure,</hi> in <hi>Number,</hi> in <hi>Scituation,</hi> in <hi>Conjunction,</hi> or <hi>Disjunction,</hi> in <hi>Diſcontinuity.</hi> And theſe being general Heads, admit of various <hi>Subdiviſions,</hi> which I muſt paſs by at this time: The urgency and importance of the following Poſtſcript, forceth me to ceaſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution at preſent, expecting opportunity hereafter to proceed, and explain what now ſeems dubious, and difficult to admit of.</p>
            <p>The Vital <hi>Spirit</hi> being thus variouſly provoked and afflicted; begets or forms various Diſeaſes, from the diverſity of <hi>Organs</hi> uſed, and <hi>Functions</hi> to be performed thereby. We may hence learn, that Diſeaſes in their multiplicity, and variation by denomination, from <hi>Parts</hi> affected, and <hi>Functions</hi> impedited; do not lye ſo wide aſunder, and differing, as the world does imagine; ſince the chief moving Principle, or obſtructed in motion; is one and the ſame in all the Faculties, but irritated to diſorder, or impedited in Vital Government: <hi>Ab unitate Animae, defluunt variae dotes ad organa ſingula.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſhewed you herein ſome part of the <hi>Learning</hi> in this Faculty, the <hi>World</hi> hath much confided in, and ventured their Lives with; which <hi>Learning</hi> I well know, and can ſtand it; and do underſtand it ſo well, that I have declined much of it, many years ago, as unſerviceable in the true Methods of Curing. I have not troubled my ſelf about bare empty Notions impracticable and unprofitable, but what are neceſſary and advantageous in Practice: that you may ſee the <hi>Life</hi> in Rectitude, Vigour and Sedateneſs, as alſo in Declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Enormity, and Perturbation; that knowing how Diſeaſes are formed, what contributes to their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>Efficiently</hi> and <hi>Materially;</hi> what is <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> in <hi>Morbous</hi> Alterations; we may the better level at them, with more Security and Certainty.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now proceed, to give you a farther Proſpect, and clearer light into this Novel Doctrine, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſome Queſtions and Doubts therein: but at this time I am prevented by the following Matter.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>LONDON, Old Southampton Buildings,</hi> over againſt <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> 
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A Treatiſe of the Scurvey. Another, of Conſumptions. Of the Venereal Lues, Gonorrhoea's, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of Pains, Inflammations, Tumours, Apoſtems, Ulcers, Cancers, Gangrens and Mortifications Internal.</p>
            <p>The Riſe and Progreſs of Phyſick. Of Health, Vigour and long Life. The Practice of Phyſick duly Regulated.</p>
            <p>All writ by <hi>EVERARD MAYNWARINGE,</hi> M. D.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52628:5"/>
            <p>'TIs a crime to be ſilent and conceal, when <hi>Information</hi> may contribute to Publick Safety: and the Rules of Prudence and Policy; give free admittance for examining the validity of ſuch Offers. Great Miniſters of State, ſometimes borrow Light from Inferiours of all ſorts; as the Nature of the Affair requires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Navy,</hi> the Bulwarks and Defence of theſe Kingdoms, are primely to be provided for; but when I conſider the fatality by <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> to be greater than that of the <hi>Sword</hi> (to the ſhame of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and Phyſicians) I cannot but reflect upon the methods and proviſion of <hi>Medicines;</hi> the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that help; but not ſo underſtood: the <hi>formality</hi> thereof look'd great, and the Stores an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable in Bulk and Weight; but not in <hi>Virtue:</hi> the performance prov'd ſmall, and little good came of it. How this comes about I might ſet forth; and the way to obviate the like Calamity enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but it is not adviſeable now; 'tis a fit time, when the <hi>Queſtion</hi> is put, by whom it belongs to inquire into this matter; then I ſhall give the account; which will give light to Counſel, for taking other meaſures in this weighty affair.</p>
            <p>I queſtion not the earneſt Care, and Sincerity of thoſe <hi>Superiours,</hi> in appointing, and charging, the moſt exquiſite performance of that great Undertaking; nor the <hi>plenary</hi> allowance for carrying on that important Work: but I may well doubt of the Praeviſion, <hi>Pharmaceutic</hi> Skill, and Expert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe <hi>ſubordinate;</hi> to whom more immediately the deſigning of Medicines was committed in truſt, as their proper buſineſs; to anſwer comprehenſively and accurately, all the requiſite intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and commodious ends (more than imagined) to compleat ſuch a deſignment: for viewing the Catalogue of Medicines, and Drugs for the laſt years Expedition; wherein I expected more than ordinary contrivance, by the time ſpent in <hi>Conſultation,</hi> and <hi>Preparation</hi> for that grand Work: yet it anſwered not my expectation in the <hi>Proſpect;</hi> nor others in <hi>Effect,</hi> whoſe lives depended there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: notwithſtanding I muſt judge it was the greateſt <hi>effort</hi> they could make in this Undertaking (elſe they were highly culpable) and I meaſure their ability by thoſe utmoſt endeavours.</p>
            <p>I thought the <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> had been ſummoned to that great Conſultation: And I believe it was <hi>ſo</hi> intended, appointed, and <hi>ſo</hi> thought to be: But I find by the reſult; there was a miſtake; that there was ſome <hi>Learning,</hi> ſome <hi>Experience,</hi> and ſome neceſſary <hi>Obſervations</hi> left out; that might have ſeaſoned all the reſt, and made that Convention of Learning, more wholſom and more heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſomething they have not met with in their Books. I believe they were ſound enough at <hi>Heart;</hi> and the <hi>Hands</hi> employed good; but the failure was in the <hi>Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it not be ſaid therefore; that ſuch a <hi>Medical</hi> proviſion for <hi>Army</hi> or <hi>Fleet;</hi> was the beſt that the Learning of <hi>England</hi> could afford: I ſhould be very ſorry, if there were not an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Phyſician to outdo all that; to deſign above it. I had a curioſity to ſee; (the Mountains bring forth) what was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of thoſe Learned <hi>Heads,</hi> and Expert <hi>Hands;</hi> ſo much <hi>Money,</hi> and ſo much <hi>Time</hi> ſpent, about that great Work; and it was as I expected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fleet, Army</hi> and <hi>Hoſpitals;</hi> are a great charge to the Kingdom; and that which indiſpenſably is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: but if the ends for which that Money is appointed and ſpent, be not anſwered and ſatisfied; much of that charge is <hi>loſt;</hi> and what is greater than that; the <hi>lives</hi> of many. The <hi>formality</hi> of Phyſick I hate, ſeparate from the <hi>reality. Fleet</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> if they venture their lives to ſave ours; we ſhould do what can be done to ſave theirs: and I know there are better <hi>Means</hi> and <hi>Methods,</hi> than hitherto practiſed for their preſervation: I were guilty if I ſhould keep ſilence.</p>
            <p>'Tis eaſie to determine what Phyſick is ſent abroad; when I ſee what is uſed at home: the Guinea <hi>Recipe's</hi> are but mean contrivances; what do you think then are the Soldiers, and the Sailers Medicines? We account it an advantage to have ſo many lives of the Enemy: and you may account it an equivalent, to ſave ſo many lives of our own Men: for whether in <hi>Battle,</hi> or in <hi>Sickneſs;</hi> 'tis much what the ſame; a dead Man, is a loſt Man. How many brave <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spirits, have languiſhed and periſhed? not for want of Medicines, but for want of <hi>true</hi> Medicine, and <hi>due</hi> adminiſtration. <hi>Hinc illae lachrimae</hi>—To dye by the fury and force of the Enemy, was what they voluntarily durſt do; but to dye by the <hi>improvidence</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> of their friends, was what they little expected. The <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Mementoes</hi> of Medical inſufficiency, are more and greater, than the <hi>Wounds</hi> and <hi>Scars</hi> of the Enemy: Truth muſt not be ſhamefac'd; nor Knowledge out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar'd, by any pedantic ſuppoſed Learning, impoſed upon the credulous Popularity. How might I now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid the <hi>World?</hi> ſince I ſee, 'tis more eaſie, and gainful to deceive, than truly to ſerve ſuch a <hi>Maſter</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ten thouſand pounds for Medicinal proviſion by Sea and <hi>Land;</hi> is a good Sum for a years ſervice: but to loſe ten thouſand Men twice told in that year by <hi>Sickneſs</hi> not in <hi>Battle,</hi> is too great a loſs. What is paſt cannot be recall'd; but for time to come, the like Calamity may be prevented. If Ears and Doors be ſhut; yet Eys and Mouths are open. I cannot wait from day to day, and ſpend my time for opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to declare farther in this matter: I muſt turn this Paper <hi>a drift,</hi> to take its chance: perhaps it may meet with ſome diſtinguiſhing kind Hand (weighing the import) to give it conduct where it ſhould arrive.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
